This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the ITE
Computer Society by its software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[music]
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Jeff Doolittle. I'm
excited to invite Philip Kylie as our
guest on the show today for a
conversation about multi-agent AI.
Topics around machine learning and
artificial intelligence have come up in
previous episodes. Some examples are
episode 633 when itar Freriedman
appeared on the show to discuss
automated testing with generative AI.
Episode 603 featured Rishi Singh on
using Genai for test code generation.
and episode 626 featured EPC Oskaya on
Genai for software architecture. Philip
Kylie leads software developer relations
at base 10. Prior to joining base 10 in
2022, he worked across software
engineering and go to market for a
variety of startups. Outside of work,
you'll find Philip practicing martial
arts, reading a new book, or cheering
for his adopted Bay Area sports teams.
Philip appeared previously on Software
Engineering Radio in episode 426 for a
discussion about writing for software
developers. Philip, welcome back to the
show.
>> Hey Jeff, thank you so much for having
me.
>> Glad you're here. Multi- aent AI. What
are we going to talk about in this
episode, Philip?
>> So today we're going to talk about how
to build things that aren't chat GPT
rappers. when you want to build what we
call at base 10 AI native software. So
that's companies that are started to
build AI native products as well as
existing companies who are adopting AI
and trying to become AI native. It's
about more than just producing a wrapper
around a single model call. It's about
composing multiple models together into
a unique and differentiated system that
can actually achieve your users's goals.
So give us more details on what you
mean. It sounds like you're saying most
teams start by doing what you're calling
a wrapper around something like chat GPT
or or maybe some other models. What
exactly does that entail?
>> Yeah. So when you look at the sort of
evolution of an AI product, you might
have something that starts out as an
add-on. Let's say you add a chat window
or a search window to your existing
product.
>> Everybody's doing this right now.
>> Exactly. But then there are a lot of
companies now that are building really
exciting and new products that weren't
possible before we added all of these AI
capabilities. So an example of that is
something like Dcript which is a tool
that I use all the time as a content
creator where I upload the video that I
made. I get a transcript and then I can
type in the transcript to actually edit
the video. This is a brand new
capability and that requires more than
one model. It requires transcription. It
requires language models. It requires
the ability to actually have a model
that takes action on an object like the
video sequence. Or if you think about a
company like I don't know source or zed
who are building code editors, it's more
than just ask a question, get an answer,
paste it into your codebase. you're
actually integrating the context of the
codebase into an agentic framework and
then powering that with multiple
different models, not just one. So all
of these products, they're using a bunch
of models. They're coordinating and
orchestrating them together. And they're
also figuring out how to do all of that
in a way that's fast for the user from a
latency perspective and creates like
feasible unit economics from a business
perspective.
>> Okay. So, for people that are just
getting started, are there benefits
sometimes to just using maybe
off-the-shelf AI tools and just wrapping
them?
>> Yeah, 100%. So, when you're getting
started and you just need to introduce
some kind of intelligence to your
product, you should absolutely go grab
an off-the-shelf model, something like
Gemini, Claude, GPT5. All of these are
great models. They're very capable. They
have a wide range of capabilities and
they're going to show you immediately
what's possible at the frontier of
intelligence. But as you advance in the
product development cycle, as you roll
out to production to hundreds of
thousands, millions of users, you start
to understand the specific needs of your
product and your audience and need to
build a tailored AI strategy to
accommodate those.
>> Okay. Now, some of this stuff is still
new. Things change so fast that I don't
want to assume that every listener knows
what the word agentic means which you
just use that word. So could you just
describe briefly what is agentic AI
[clears throat] as opposed to just what
we've thought of as like chat AIs this
sort of stuff that's been common and and
is now very wellnown.
>> Absolutely. We've got a lot of fun
buzzwords here and that's what helps us
you know feel smart in the AI industry.
But I'm actually wearing a shirt. This
is not a video podcast. I'm wearing a
shirt right now that says artificially
intelligent. And I use all these
buzzwords to feel naturally intelligent.
Agentic AI basically just means going
from an AI that produces information to
an AI that takes action. At a technical
level, this is implemented through
something called function calling or
tool use where you add the capability of
your model to take a list of tools, pick
which one it wants to use and return
that selection as well as inputs to the
tool. Then your agent framework or your
product environment is going to be able
to take that suggestion from the model
like hey do this action and actually
execute that function call use that tool
to take whatever action the agent has
suggested.
>> Okay. So I might have an AI experience
that just gives me information like chat
GPT but no action is being taken. The
next step once we go to an agent now it
can do something with a tool a function
call as you said and now in this episode
we're also going to talk about multi-
aent AI that sounds like even the next
level of composition so what happens now
at that level yeah so chat GPT itself
has become increasingly agentic for
example if you think about chat GPT pro
which does all of the searching ahead of
the reasoning chain doing a web search
is an agentic action
Your model is not capable of simply just
doing that. You need to build a scaffold
around it. You need to tell it that it
has access to this tool. Tell it that it
can request this tool and then wait for
a response from it. And when we think
about composing multiple agents
together, that really comes from having
more than one model in many cases. So
everyone when we're talking about
generative AI, we love to talk about
large language models, LLMs, stuff like
that, GPT5, that Gemini 2.5 and the open
source ones, you know, Kimmy Quinn, all
those guys. But there are a lot of other
modalities out there in the generative
AI industry. We can create images and
videos from text. We can use embeddings
to encode the semantic meaning of text
and use that to do retrieval, use that
to do memory, context, recommendation,
all that kind of stuff. We can interface
with the user through new modalities
like voice. So there are all these other
capabilities outside of the core
language model intelligence that we need
to compose together in order to build
one of these more advanced systems. So
speaking of a more advanced system,
there's an example we talked about
before the show that it might be helpful
to dive into which is the D&D AI
assistant. So let's talk through maybe
if a team is just getting started as you
mentioned before, maybe they want to use
some off-the-shelf models. So let's
start there and then walk us through a
story of how this team might grow. Like
let's like maybe eventually generates
video and all this crazy stuff. Let's
start simple, right? Maybe it's all
textbased and it's just driving stuff
and then how would that begin to grow
more into this agentic flow and then how
might that grow into multimodel flow and
then when would you maybe want to
transition from using a GPT5 or a claude
to using a different model maybe one of
your own?
>> This is a great question. So, this is a
problem that product teams face all the
time is they have this vision, right,
which is in the case, you know, Jeff and
I, we were kind of joking around before
the show like what would be a fun AI
product that I would enjoy building and
I play a lot of Dungeons and Dragons D
and D, or at least I used to before I
was working in AI all the time. So, as a
D&D game, you have a bunch of your
friends together, all playing different
characters, and then one person who's
the game manager, the dungeon master
who's in charge of actually
orchestrating the game. You can think of
the job as the dungeon master is almost
being a video game engine for all your
friends. You're making the actual
actions happen. So, we're thinking,
well, what if you could just do AI
instead so that everyone could play
instead of one person having to kind of
orchestrate the game? Hm.
>> If I was to build a V0 of this kind of
system, I would think first from a
product perspective, okay, I want to
build an assistant for a dungeon master.
I want to make it easier and more fun to
do this role rather than trying to
replace it right away with an entire
endto-end system. And so what that would
probably look like is a textbased
interface. Like you said, I can just
spin up a large language model. I can
use something off the shelf. And then
the first component that I'm going to
need to introduce is some kind of
context and some kind of memory. So I'm
going to want to be able to feed my
model information like what are the
stats of different monsters that they
might run across and what are the
equipment that they might need? What is
the terrain that they're in? All that
kind of stuff. So for that we start to
think about something called retrieval
augmented generation or rag which has
been a really hot topic in the industry
for the last couple years. With rag you
can introduce new context into your
model dynamically at runtime. And what
that lets you do is ground the model in
facts and reality or in our case a
specific fictional world and you achieve
that using embedding models.
>> Okay. So now we've got stage one. We've
got our assistant that helps the human
dungeon master, I guess, work less,
right? They're getting help. Now, what's
the next phase of evolution here? You
know, where real quick, what's the
product vision? Where are we heading?
And then we can go back to the steps
we're taking to get there. Like, where
does this thing end?
>> Yeah. So, the the product vision that
we're building toward here, and you
know, again, this is just completely
hypothetical, is is what if you could
have a a system where my friends and I
show up and we turn on this system and
we can all just play D and D together.
We come up with characters, we come up
with scenarios, and no matter what we
do, the game is able to update itself.
It's able to interact with us. It's able
to create characters for us to interact
with. basically an entire generative
gaming experience delivered exactly the
same way that an experienced human GM
would, but in a way that you know all of
us can play together instead of one
person having to do that role
>> and maybe it's creatively generating the
story but maybe eventually it generates
video snippets or
>> Exactly. Yeah.
So on the modality side where when you
build systems like this that you're
trying to deploy to a large number of
people and and have be a very engaging
AI experience, you really quickly have
to move beyond text. So no one gets
together to play D and D by email. You
get together in a room and you're
talking and you're rolling dice. And so
you want to introduce new capabilities
to the system. First off, you need to be
able to transcribe the conversation. You
need to be able to diorize the
conversation, which means attribute
who's saying what lines so you know
what's happening with each character.
And then you also need to give voice to
the AI. You need it to be able to speak
back to the players, not just produce
text on screen. So these are all great
examples of the kind of work that has to
happen in a multimodal agent system
where you're bringing in inputs from
different sources. And then we can also
see a little bit more concretely what it
means to be an agent. For example,
rolling dice. That's a huge part of Dn
D. It determines whether or not your
attacks hit, whether or not you're able
to take certain actions. And it's very
easy for a computer to quote unquote
roll a dice. All they need to do is run
a little script to generate a random
number. But an LLM is not capable of
generating a random number on its own.
If you ask it for a random number, the
distribution is going to be heavily
weighted because it's predicting a
likely next token, not a random next
token.
>> Right?
>> So, we can introduce a tool. Let's say
we have a Python function called roll a
dice.
>> And you tell the function how many sides
the dice has. So you would as the game
goes on the agent system would very
frequently say like oh I as the GM am
simulating a monster attacking the
player and whenever an attack happens I
need to roll a 20sided dice to see
whether or not it hits. So I would call
this function roll dice and I need to
pass it the argument 20 and that'll be
the actual response from the model. The
model won't output the monster hit the
player or the monster missed. The model
will output, hey, please roll a 20-sided
dice. The agent framework is going to
pick that up, do that action, give it
back to the model, and then you have a
new prompt. You have a new generation
cycle that's going to say, "Okay, it was
a 19. The monster hit the player." And
then it's going to take that information
and speak it out loud. So you can see
how we're very quickly moving to a very
complex system where all of these models
have to work together in sequence very
quickly and they are passing information
back and forth in a sort of contextual
memory layer rather than relying on a
single prompt to run this entire system
end to end.
>> Yeah. So composing together different
tools and different agents that are
specifically capable in particular ways
rather than just throwing it at chat GPT
and expecting it to, as you said,
generate random numbers, for example,
which it's not going to be going to be
good at. Right.
>> Exactly. It's always very surprising
what capabilities AI models have and
don't have. Sometimes I ask a model to
oneshot an entire page of code that I've
been thinking about and it just gets it
done perfectly on the first try. But
there's other very simple actions that
models can't do unless you give it the
tools to do so.
>> Absolutely. I've attempted generate
system just to see what would happen.
And you wouldn't be surprised that it's
just a big mess by giving it that much
all at once. Then of course there's the
opposite end of the spectrum. How many
bees are in blueberry? But you know when
you consider token size and things of
that nature, people get bent at a shape.
Oh, the AI can't tell you that. Well,
it's a tool. It may not be able to do
that, but it's really good at a bunch of
other things.
>> Exactly. And you can always use tool
calls to address the weakness of a
foundation model. If you give it a
Python script that says, "Hey, do this
substring matching problem." That's a
very simple Python script to implement,
it can write that script for you and
then run that script for you and then
tell you how many Ps are in Blueberry.
You just need to give it the access to
the tools in the runtime environment to
do that.
>> Yeah. Interesting. So, there's a few
directions we can go, but I want to
start with let's say we've gotten this
Dungeons and Dragons AI agent to a
certain point, but everything we've done
so far, we're using off-the-shelf
models. When would you start to make
that transition and what would you do?
>> Yeah, so there's a few places where I
see AI teams start to run into some of
the limitations of off-the-shelf models.
>> A big one is domain specific quality. So
when we think about our system, we are
trying to for example have a fun role-
playinging voice where it's going to be
adventurous and exciting and engaging in
the same way that say a book or movie
dialogue would be. Your average
off-the-shelf model does not have very
much personality like that. You can get
a long way with prompting, but you can
always tell when some text is written by
a certain model.
>> Mh. So, this is even more important, of
course, in in real world systems. I work
with a lot of companies in the health
care space where they're investing a ton
of money in training and fine-tuning
models that do better and do better
enough that they can actually be used in
the real world for both front and back
office healthcare things. It's important
in finance. It's important in education.
There are all these places where you
want to train or fine-tune a model so
that it performs better in your domain.
So that's that's the first place is
domain specific quality makes people
start looking. The second reason people
start looking is latency. We're now
talking about four or five models
running and sometimes running multiple
calls each in between every single user
action. So, I ask the system, you know,
hey, my guy swung his sword. Do you hit
the hydra? And if it's waiting four or 5
seconds to tell me the answer to that,
it's not a very good player experience.
So, latency is important in literally
every single part of AI. It's especially
important in voice AI when people are
speaking to a system in real time. And
then the third thing is economics. Like
if I'm making this app and it is blowing
up and going viral and I am paying
linearly more in token costs for every
single user who signs up and start using
it, it's going to get really expensive
really quick. Of course, there's a ton
of money in the AI space. I can always
raise around and and just continue to
gain market share. But at some point,
I'm gonna have to start thinking about
the unit economics of my product and
making sure that it makes sense and that
I'm operating a sustainable business in
the long term.
>> What's interesting is those three
factors you just mentioned were true
before everybody started adopting AI.
[laughter]
It's it sounds like it's just software
engineering.
>> That's true. That's maybe if you take
nothing else away from this episode is
that AI engineering is just software
engineering with some new tricks to it.
I think a perfect example of this is we
see so many times where we have a model
that we've optimized, we've shaved every
single millisecond off of the prefill
and the decode and all these inference
steps. We've put it up on some
autoscaling GPU clusters, colllocated it
next to the customer. You know, we've
gotten everything perfect down to the
milliseconds and we're like, "Hey, the
benchmark for this is 200 milliseconds."
and they come back to us and say, "Dude,
I'm seeing 250 300 in production." Like,
what's going on? It's the client code.
It's just session reuse or it's some
pass through, some redirect proxy that's
adding a few dozen milliseconds here or
there. So there's so many times when the
problems that we run into in production
around these AI systems are less related
to the model itself or the inference
service or any of the cool stuff that I
like to talk about and just pure
ordinary software engineering that still
needs to be done to an incredibly high
degree of quality and craft in this new
industry.
>> It makes sense and you talked about
multiple steps. For example, if I have
an agent that's orchestrating a
five-step process and those steps can't
be parallelized, well, any one step can
slow the entire It doesn't matter if
four out of five steps or 20
milliseconds if one of the steps is
2,000, for example.
>> Exactly.
>> Yeah. So, we're right back to that. So,
with these systems, let's switch gears a
little bit. There's obviously a lot of
information passing back and forth now
between the human and these systems. If
we're talking about Dungeons and Dragons
and in a game, maybe the risk isn't
super high of nefarious things happening
with our data. But the more we hand off
capabilities to an agent, seems like
trust becomes more and more important.
So speak some to how do we handle issues
around sensitive data or around agents
that maybe have power that is a little
dangerous to be handing them. You know,
I think of the agent I saw the other day
that did a rmspace-rf
slash. And fortunately, it had the right
path afterwards, but I sort of had that
moment of, "Oh my gosh, what if it just
was slash?" I would have been in big
trouble.
Absolutely. So, there's a few different
things here. I think number one is just
making sure that you understand the
tools you're giving the agent access to.
You can choose what tools it has. if it
doesn't have access to a given tool that
it can't take that action. The second
thing is human in the loop for more
sensitive actions. So let's say I was
making a stock trading agent that was
going to manage my portfolio on my
behalf. Maybe I want to have it text me
every time it's going to make a trade
for more than $1,000 so that I can just
give it a quick thumbs up and make sure
it's not doing something dumb. The final
thing is, you know, more on the eval
side, like making sure that we're
rigorously testing our models, making
sure that we're evaluating our models on
the actual domain that we're going to be
deploying them in, rather than just
looking at the launch blog post and
being like, "Wow, this has a higher
version number than the last model, so
it must be better." And just [laughter]
cowboying it straight into production.
So, it's a multi-step process. It's
having a clear understanding of what
good looks like, having some safeguards
in place around what systems you're
giving it access to at all, and then
having that sort of yellow light system
of the human in the loop to prevent any
kind of nefarious actions. You know, in
general, I find myself pretty trusting
of AI agents. The folks working on
alignment are doing a pretty good job
these days. So I think of it more around
the idea of preventing mistakes rather
than preventing nefarious behavior. For
nefarious behavior that that's still
coming from humans. You know, we have
all the same problems around, you know,
with base 10, we got a lot of GPUs
people sign up try and like crypto mine
and stuff. So there's all of the same
human nefarious problems that you have
to solve in this agent world. And then
you have to add in the safeguards
against mistakes from the AI system as
well.
>> So two terms you mentioned I want to
make sure we define for listeners. Evals
and alignment. Can you describe what
those terms mean in case they're
unfamiliar to listeners?
>> Absolutely. So an eval is a quality
benchmark. Generally it's used in the
industry to mean one that you've created
yourself or one that you've created with
your own product in mind. So, an example
of an eval for a D&D system would be,
let's say you have a model that is
deciding what level of monster to give
your characters and you want to make
sure it's evenly matched. So, you might
make a set of good party setups and a
set of good monsters and make sure that
the model is able to match them
appropriately. That's an example of a
domain specific eval for alignment.
That's more of a philosophical question
in the AI industry of making sure that
our models are prompted and are
constrained and and fine-tuned to be
helpful, to be harmless, to be useful.
So that's, you know, making sure that
the models aren't swearing, aren't
creating negative images, all that kind
of stuff. And they're related problems.
You can have evals for alignment but
yeah generally the models that get
released to the public these days are
quite well aligned. They are very
rigorously tested and we've seen them be
you know very very useful in general. So
that's why I said you know alignment is
pretty good these days.
>> Yeah. To what extent is alignment being
done by retraining the internal models
versus, you know, maybe additional
pipeline checks, you know, before you
actually hit the model.
>> Yeah. So again, all of these sort of
processes are going to be a multi-stage
thing.
>> You have first off the curation of the
training data. So it's hard for a model,
not impossible, but it's hard for a
model to generalize outside of the
training data. So if you make sure that
your data is is curated to be the sort
of things that you want the model to
reproduce, that's great. The second
thing is reinforcement learning
fine-tuning, which is basically where
you are giving the model a reward
function and saying, "Hey, I'm going to
reward positive behavior and I'm going
to ding negative behavior." That's a
very powerful alignment tool. Then what
happens is after you train a model, you
create a base model, which is basically
a pool of intelligence, but it's not
instruct tuned. So it's not necessarily
ready to have a conversation yet. It's
more just able to complete sentences. So
you take that base model and through
that instruction tuning process, you do
additional fine-tuning to make sure that
it's handling instructions correctly.
for example, you know, it's refusing to
help people understand how to make
chemical weapons. And then finally, at
the deployment level, it is the
responsibility of the developer to make
sure that their models being used
appropriately. There's a lot of new
security issues and new avenues of
research here. I think Simon Wilson's
written a lot about prompt injection,
which is the idea of like an AI system
where you're able to take a a model
that's designed to do one specific thing
like Dungeons and Dragons and inject a
prompt that makes it forget its original
context and say, "Hey, instead I want
you to help me like understand how to
build weapons."
>> Right? So there's a lot of stages and a
lot of interesting research there. But
for you know most practical purposes the
models that are in production today are
quite reliable. They are quite well
aligned and we're seeing them get a lot
of success across all kinds of domains.
There's always going to be funny issues.
I saw a year or so ago some guy like
tricked the Chevy chatbot into selling
him a car for a dollar. There's always
going to be fun prompt injection things
like that that point out some of the
holes in these systems, but those get
patched over pretty quickly.
>> Yeah, fun. Unless you're Chevy in that
case, in which case not so fun. But
>> I don't think he actually got the car.
>> It's probably true.
>> It's just a chatbot.
>> Yeah. Although I have seen the cases
where customer data has been leaked from
doing weird things like using the Apache
language that almost nobody understands,
but the LLM did and it somehow,
>> you know, anyway. So there's Yeah,
there's interesting stuff there. So, we
talked before about maybe you get to a
point where it's expensive or there's
latency issues and so maybe you need to
host your own model, but at that point
you're going to take on all of the
burden of what we just described, are
you not?
>> Yeah. So, there's the sort of AI
engineering layer of the evals of the
system building of the coordination of
the models, the prompting, the context,
all that kind of stuff. And you're going
to have to do that work whether you're
using open- source or closed source or
custom models that you trained yourself.
But when you do go to open source models
or you do go to those custom models
because you're looking for that domain
specific quality, you're looking for
those unit economics, you're looking for
that better latency, you add a new type
of engineering challenge and that's
inference engineering. So basically you
have this entire domain of both model
performance runtime optimization and
multicloud GPU infrastructure
orchestration that you've added into
your engineering team's workload in
order to make all that stuff happen.
>> Great. Now again in not assuming
everybody is all caught up on all this
AI stuff used another word that I think
it's useful to define. What is
inference?
>> Inference is everything. Haven't you
seen the billboard? [laughter] No.
So
>> all over the city. Yes.
>> Yes. For those listeners not in San
Francisco, we've spent a lot on buses
and billboards recently talking about
inference. What is inference? So there's
two phases of a model's life. There's
the training phase, which is kind of
what we were talking about where you're
feeding data to the model, helping it
get better. And then there's the
inference phase. With inference, the
model weights, or the actual underlying
values and architecture of the model,
those are frozen. They're done. the
model's not going to change. What you
need to do now is actually use the model
to generate responses to user queries
and that's inference. So two phases.
Training is creating the model.
Inference is actually using the model in
production. One misconception I'll
address really quick about machine
learning systems. And I've heard this
from the highest levels of big
enterprises even in conferences and
stuff is the idea that somehow a model
learns while it's live in
[clears throat] production.
>> That's I think a very easy misconception
to have because it's literally called
machine learning. So isn't it learning
more?
>> No. Creating a system that actually
adapts to what's happening in production
takes a ton of engineering work to
gather that data and continuously
retrain and redeploy these models. There
are definitely companies that have been
able to build that kind of sophisticated
system. Obviously all the Frontier Labs,
OpenAI, Claude, all those are able to
use those free user chats and and
continue to make their model faster.
Sorry, not faster but better. But yeah,
the thing to understand about inference
in its purest form is that the model is
fixed. It's done. It's fully baked. And
now you're just using it over and over
in production to actually generate
business value and so few users.
>> Right? Now, let's take that a little
further. Let's say I want to build my
own model and then, you know, I do the
training and now it's locked. Right?
Now, now we're doing inference. The
model's not changing. But I want to use
multi- aent AI to build the next model.
So maybe I have a judging AI that knows
how to, you know, do my evals, right?
And make sure there's alignment
according to some other quality
characteristics that I care about. How
would I create a pipeline that would now
allow me to say, hey, start maybe
autotraining the next model and seeing
how it performs according to this
automated just can you carry that
analogy forward and and are people doing
that? And how might people do that for
themselves if they want to take this,
you know, that far?
>> Yeah, that's one of the very most
sophisticated setups that a company
might have. Generally, you see these
setups at companies where creating new
foundation models is core to their
business. Like they are research labs.
And in those cases, absolutely. What
they're doing is they're taking each
iteration of the model, deploying it
into production, seeing how it works,
gathering user feedback, and using that
to create fine-tuning data sets, using
that to create training data sets, and
putting those into the next version of
the model. They're also doing a lot of
other stuff. They're doing architecture
research. They're trying to expand
things to larger scale, trying to get
more and higher quality training data
from other sources. So it's one small
part of a larger system of making better
and better models. But the way you set
up that system is like you said, you
have the model running in production.
You have a data gathering mechanism. You
have that evaluation mechanism. You're
generally not going to be like
retraining your model overnight. That's
more of a setup that was common in the
ML world where you were sort of
continuously retraining these very small
couple hundred million parameter type
models and redeploying them for
increased predictive accuracy. the
iteration cycles are slower in the AI
world where you know you might be
releasing new models on a a monthly
cadence or a multimonth cadence is is
what we generally see from the best labs
>> right but in the meantime I imagine
there are multiple potential models that
don't fulfill whatever the criteria
might be they don't meet the eval
they're not aligned properly they're too
easy to jailbreak whatever it might be
and then they select from the ones that
fulfill the requirements and that's the
one that gets released
>> absolutely Absolutely. Absolutely. There
is unfortunately a lot of work that has
to be thrown away in a non-deterministic
system, but ultimately you are able to
get to the best and not just get stuck
at like some local maximum.
>> And as soon as you're going to create
your own models though, you're going to
have to carry that burden whether you
automate it or not.
>> Yeah, absolutely. So that's why a lot of
companies choose to instead of creating
models from scratch do lightweight fine
tunes on top of existing models. So I've
talked a few times about this idea of a
foundation model that's going to be one
of the big models from a major lab. In
the open- source world this might be
something like Llama, Mistral, Quen,
Kimmy. You're taking one of these
foundation models and then you are
applying a much smaller data set. These
models are trained on trillions of
tokens. Like think you know every book
ever written, everything ever said on
the internet. That kind of scale of
data.
>> Yeah,
>> fine-tuning data can be much smaller in
scale. You might have a few tens or
hundreds of thousands of questions and
answer pairs that are relevant to the
behavior that you want to generate. And
you're able to create a lightweight
modification to these models. You know,
AI inference is just matrix math. It's
just a bunch of matrix multiplications.
Your fine-tune is just one more matrix
in that sequence that everything's
getting filtered through to slightly
adjust the behavior of the model. And
creating one of those, while still a lot
of engineering work and still something
that should only be invested in after a
lot of other things in the system are
figured out is hundreds or thousands of
times faster, cheaper, and easier than
training entire models from scratch.
>> Yeah, that makes sense. So, let's say
our Dungeons and Dragons game is really
taking off now and and we're hitting up
on some of those factors you mentioned
before that might cause you to say, you
know, whether it's the economic factors
or it's the latency factors, we're
starting to hit on those and now we need
to transition to what you've described
before as a dedicated deployment. So can
you unpack for our listeners what
exactly those next steps might be using
that example to move from you know say
and maybe you still use a foundation
model for some aspects of it but there's
some piece that you say we're going to
move this now to a dedicated deployment.
What does that mean and what does that
entail?
>> Absolutely. So to start with we're just
doing a little bit more software
engineering. We've always had
multi-tenant services and single tenant
services. As a AI model API offtheshelf,
what I'm getting from someone like
OpenAI is I'm getting one endpoint.
Everyone else has the same endpoint.
We're all hitting it and our traffic
gets mixed together and served. But when
I want to start doing my own thing,
having really stable P99 latencies and
buying my tokens in bulk, like going to
Costco, rather than one at a time, like
going to the gas station, I'm going to
need to set up my own GPUs to run these
models. And this is why we've switched
to open models, of course, here, because
I can't just take the GPT5 weights and
run it. They won't let me. It's their
it's their secret sauce.
>> Yes. But if I take one of these open-
source models like Quen or something and
I put it up on the GPU, now it's only my
users who are using it. So if someone
else, if my friend startup gets a spike
of traffic, their traffic isn't
affecting mine. It's the same noisy
neighbor problem we've had in in past
APIs, it's just magnified by the fact
that now our APIs are backed by these
huge and expensive GPUs doing these very
intensive calculations.
So yeah, I'm going to have to secure
these GPUs. cuz I have to like actually
go get them, go lease them or rent them.
And then I'm going to need to install a
runtime on these GPUs so that I can
actually serve the model. And then I'm
going to need to scale up and down
replicating this system over and over
again in order to meet the demands where
maybe more people are playing on Friday
and Saturday night. So I need more GPUs
then I need fewer GPUs at 10:00 on a
Tuesday when everyone should be at work.
>> Right? Another term you just used again
in the interest of clarification. You
said weights and you said you know GPT5
we we don't get to use their weights.
They won't let us. That's their secret
sauce. Can you unpack that? What are
weights?
>> Absolutely. So a large language model or
or most generative AI models like I said
it's all just a bunch of matrix math.
>> Right.
>> So the weights are a giant matrix. If
you think about a model having say a
trillion parameters, I'm sure we've
heard about model size being talked
about in terms of parameters. A
parameter is just one number. If you
think about a simple logistic regression
model where it's like c= ax + b y a and
b are parameters. That is a two
parameter model. And you can scale up
that example to okay now I have a
trillion parameters. Each one is just a
number. And these numbers are in this
neural network. They weigh or they
adjust the weighted probability of a
certain token being produced. So that's
why they're called the model weights.
The parameters are are influencing or
weighing on the output of the model. And
so they're the weights. The weights of a
model is what determines whether or not
a model's open source or closed source.
Closed source models, you don't know
what the weights are. Open source
models, you do. They're the weights are
on hugging face. You can download them,
you can use them, you can run them in
your own company, you can run them on
your own hardware.
>> Great. So, what other pieces are needed
if you want to build and host? Let's
start with your own dedicated inference
platform and then maybe we want to grow
beyond that into a dedicated multi- aent
platform or at least pieces of it.
>> Yeah. So, the two pieces are the
infrastructure and the runtime. The
infrastructure again is like getting the
GPUs, orchestrating them. The runtime is
really exciting because with these model
weights that you have, you have various
options for things like inference
engines. So some popular tools are VLM,
SGLANG, Tensor RTLM. There's also
transformers and diffusers, which are
the sort of underlying technologies
based on PyTorch that run these
generative models. Transformers for most
things. Diffusers are going to be for
your image models that turn noise into
an image.
>> So what's VLM? What's SGLAN? What do all
these things do? Well, they're inference
engines. So you load the weights into
the engine. You put that system in a
container, just a Docker container.
Again, we're just doing real software
engineering here. Put that on a GPU. And
the inference engine is actually
responsible for running those matrix
multiplications to produce inference on
the GPU. And your choice of inference
engine, the way you configure the
inference engine has a massive impact on
the actual speed and throughput of your
eventual production system. Because
these are all very complex calculations.
They're bottlenecked in various places.
For example, your time to first token or
the time it takes to generate that first
little bit of output is going to be
mostly based on compute, like how many
flops you have on your GPU. And then
your decode, which is what's going to
generate every single one of those
subsequent tokens, is going to be bound
on your memory bandwidth on the GPU. So,
we have two different bottlenecks right
next to each other in these two phases
of inference. You have to figure out,
you know, systems and algorithms and
optimizations to get around those
bottlenecks to be able to serve all this
traffic really fast and to be able to
serve it in a way that utilizes the GPU
to the maximum capacity so that you're
not wasting money on underutilized
hardware. That's inference engineering
right there. It's it's both getting the
GPU but also using it effectively. And
it's a really exciting thing to work on.
>> May seem like a really basic question,
but why do we need GPUs? Why aren't CPUs
sufficient in this space?
>> So in the ML world and when I joined B
10, we were a a very inference focused
company four years ago, but we still
were working a lot with ML models. Like
I ran all kinds of XG boost models and
stuff on CPUs and they ran fast, but
those things were tiny.
>> So the models today, first off, they're
huge. So you know these billions,
trillions parameters, you need a ton of
memory to support them. So that's where
the GPUs come in with their hundreds of
gigabytes in the case of B200's of high
bandwidth memory. And then more
importantly, they have the tensor cores.
So as we've talked about, model
inference is a matrix math linear
algebra type of system. And so these
GPUs are optimized to do all of these
things in parallel. GPUs are throughput
machines. They're great at parallelizing
this kind of math. You actually can run
models on CPUs. It's just really slow.
If you have like a local CPU and some
local RAM, I mean, if you have a
Raspberry Pi, you can run a really tiny
model. It's just going to be slow.
>> And for our production systems, we're
trying to make things real time.
>> Yeah. You talk about a matrix and you
know, for those who took calculus BC in
the United States, what we call it, or
calculus C, you know what matrices are,
but those are typically 2 by two. How
big are these matrices or matrices that
we're talking about in this space?
>> Billions.
So
>> well but it just said the
dimensionality.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Dimensionality you know
hundreds of thousands of dimensions in
each direction.
>> So we can't even conceive of four
dimensions in our head. So So
>> the thing is like you don't actually I
mean there's a lot of math here.
>> Don't get me wrong. And I certainly have
learned a lot but have a ton more to
learn about the underlying mechanics of
all of this at the very lowest level.
But I got a B in linear algebra. I got a
B in statistics in in college. Like I am
good at math but not great at it. You
don't have to be some Einstein level
mathematician to grasp the mechanics of
inference and to understand how to make
it faster. It's just like we talked
about software engineering introducing
constraints to the system and iterative
experimentation and evaluation. So the
math's important. It's really fun and
interesting to learn. But as someone
working in the system every day, I'm,
you know, living proof right here on a
podcast talking about it that you don't
have to be a PhD in math to understand
how some of this stuff works.
>> And as you said before, traditional
software engineering challenges still
apply in this context. Correct.
>> Absolutely. Like most of AI engineering
is just new versions of software
engineering with some fun
non-deterministic behavior sprinkled in.
Are there any specific aspects of
software engineering that really should
be emphasized if you are working on
self-hosting or or building multi- aent
AI systems?
>> I think a big one is the idea of
configuration. So when we think about a
model inference engine, there are
hundreds of different parameters that
you can adjust. You can adjust the
quantization. You can adjust the
speculation algorithm. You can adjust
the batch sizes, the sequence lengths.
There are all temperature, whatever.
>> Yes, the temperature. Exactly. There are
all of these different configurations
that you can mess with. What's the best
one? Well, it it depends. M so one thing
that I've seen happen over the last
couple years and and is a trend that is
continuing is the idea of a lot of these
configurations used to be set at deploy
time and now they're set dynamically at
runtime. Mhm.
>> So as we think about software
infrastructure, a big trend over the
industry for a long time has been how do
we take something that used to be static
and make it dynamic and make it adjust
to the real world conditions it's
operating under. The exact same thing is
happening in inference engineering where
we're going from, okay, we're going to
run one benchmark for performance and
we're going to do as well as we can on
that benchmark and then we're just going
to roll out this system to having a
system that automatically adjusts to
scale to the nature of the traffic and
to the performance it's seeing in order
to just continually improve.
>> Well, that speaks to the importance of
observability.
Can you speak some to how are companies
doing observability in this space to
ensure that they're getting good results
out of these systems?
>> We use all the standard observability
tools. We have our our graphana
dashboards and our sentry alerts and
stuff. Again, if these models are going
to be core missionritical parts of your
software stack, they need to be treated
like core mission critical parts of your
software stack. [laughter] You should
get paged when latencies elevate. You
should get paged when GPU nodes cycle.
So, a big part of our observability is
around the performance. Just making sure
that we're keeping an eye on traffic,
keeping an eye on latencies, keeping
those steady, keeping an eye on errors,
making sure that like there aren't too
many requests timing out, that kind of
stuff. And there's also the AI
observability layer in terms of the
model outputs and and making sure that
those are continuously of high quality.
I have a lot less experience there being
that I work more on the infrastructure
side than on the AI engineering side.
But from my understanding, it's
basically keeping an eye on those eval
numbers, making sure that they're
trending in the right direction, and
also just listening to your users, like
just having open lines of communication,
making sure that users are continuously
happy with the service that they're
getting from the models. What other
responsibilities do you have to take on
when you either host your own models or
you're building multi- aent systems?
>> So GPUs are great technology like I
would not have this career in in
inference engineering without the
existence of GPUs. So I'm very thankful
for them. But they're also kind of a
pain to work with sometimes. If anyone's
ever run a long running task on GPUs in
production and in a data center, they
know that GPUs do not stay up 99.99%
of the time. But if nothing close to
that, like you're lucky to have a couple
nines in there. But if you are building
say a assistant for doctors that every
single doctor in America is going to use
to make sure that they're delivering the
best possible care which is something
that one of our customers has built then
you need to have that extremely high
reliability because if you're
interfering with a medical process that
that can literally be life or death. And
so the big responsibility that you have
on the inference engineering and
infrastructure side that you're taking
on when you switch to models that you're
running yourself is to go from these
very flaky and unreliable hardware
systems into a software layer that
orchestrates all this. Has active active
reliability. Goes in multiple clouds
just in case one of your cloud providers
goes down. goes in multiple regions so
you're close to every user can fail over
from cluster to cluster can cycle nodes
automatically when they have issues this
software orchestration layer becomes
your responsibility as well and is very
very critical because reliability is one
of the differentiators today in the AI
industry everyone complains when chat
GPT goes down everyone's always asking
on Twitter like hey does this model seem
dumb today or you know what's going on
under the hood put in the system when
you take that in-house you do gain
control over all of that but again you
also gain all of that responsibility and
depending what you're working on that
can be a very very heavy responsibility
I
>> mean everything you just said about
orchestration across multiple regions
and failover and high availability that
still just sounds like software
engineering
>> it's
>> we can't just sprinkle AI on it Philip
and just have it work
>> there's a reason they let me on software
engineering radio instead of having to
create AI engineering radio. It's a
field that I think should be very
welcoming to everyone with a background
in any kind of software engineering work
because it's all needed. Again, we got
to do the same stuff that we've done for
all of our previous systems. We have to
adapt it. Of course, the systems are
bigger, they're faster, they're less
deterministic, but we have to do a lot
of the same engineering work as an
industry to make these things grow and
scale that we did in every single one of
the last generations of technology.
>> Yeah. So, let's say someone wants to
start transitioning. they've been adding
chat bots on top of their existing
systems and now they're listening to
this show or they've been you know
reading other things and they're saying
I want to get into this agentic world
and I want to start looking even at
multi- aent AI what should they do to
get started or what approaches might
they take I would really recommend an
approach of iterative experimentation I
think the easiest way for this to go
wrong is to decide that you want to
build the single greatest AI AI system
to ever exist and you're going to do it
today. Obviously, you should have a lot
of ambition working in this space. This
space is growing fast. People are
building unbelievable things. But it's
important to stay grounded in the
day-to-day work of how can I make
something a little bit better today.
That might be introducing a new
modality, saying like, okay, I'm going
to add voice to my chat. It might be
introducing new context, saying, I'm
going to give my agent access to a new
type of data that it hasn't had before.
And as we've been talking about, it
could be something entirely unrelated to
AI. You could be making better tools for
agents to use. You could be cleaning up
your docs so that it's easier to find
out what information to pull. You could
be optimizing the latency of your
networking stack so that you're not
having users hang out for 50
milliseconds every time they want to
make a call. There's so much engineering
work to do around making AI systems
better and more reliable both within and
outside of AI engineering that there's
some place for everyone to contribute.
>> So, Philip, what's been your journey?
How did you get into this space?
>> Like I said, everyone has a role to play
in the AI engineering industry and mine
was joining pretty early actually. I
joined this company called Base 10. Back
then it was a pre-revenue team and we
were working on ML AI inference. I wish
that I could tell you that I had some
like great market insight where I knew
this was going to be huge, you know, a
year before chat GPT came out. I did
not. I was looking for a job. I wanted a
stable paycheck so I could pay rent. And
my only thesis, if I had one, was like,
hey, these people are really kind and
really smart and I'd like to work with
them on whatever it is they're doing. So
I joined this little company and I was
very fortunate to have the opportunity
to learn on the job over the last four
years to transition into more of this
developer relations and inference
engineering space where I'm able to work
directly with some of the fastest
growing AI companies in the world where
I'm able to go speak at like Nvidia GTC
and reinvent and AI engineer awards fair
and some of these great conferences and
talk about the things that I'm learning
from our engineers.
about how to make these systems faster
and more reliable. So yeah, it's been a
great journey growing with the industry
from getting in even ahead of chat GPT
blowing up and having the opportunity to
learn along the way.
>> That's great. And tell us a little bit
about what B 10 does and how that
relates to multi- aent AI.
>> Absolutely. So B 10 is an influence
platform and we've come a long way since
that tiny company I joined four years
ago. Actually, as we're recording today,
I'm super happy that we're announcing
our series D financing. We raised at
over a $2 billion valuation, which is
really exciting.
>> Congratulations.
>> And that's just a validation of this
industry that we're in and the
importance of inference in this market.
So, what B 10 does is think of any fast
growing AI startup you can think of.
They're probably either using or should
be using base 10 to run the inference
that powers their product. So they're
taking their open source and their
custom models, deploying them with us.
We're helping them make them faster,
lower latency, more scalability, more
throughput, all of that kind of stuff.
And it's been a really cool place to
work because I've learned about every
different modality of model, every
different use case. I now know way too
much about where you can find GPUs from
Finland to Australia. We've got this
cool map where we just kind of show
where all everybody's hunting for GPUs.
Yeah.
>> Exactly. And and what we've been able to
do with this multicloud capacity
management software that we've built is
we're able to kind of pull the GPUs from
10 plus different cloud providers, have
a single unified layer of compute that
we're able to draw from and use that to
run missionritical inference for all
these super fast growing AI companies
and now also for larger companies,
enterprises, which has been just the
most interesting learning experience
I've been a part of in my entire career.
Great. Well, if people want to find out
more about what you're up to, where can
they go?
>> So, I've done a lot of work. I've been
working on it for 10 years. I've got SEO
on my name. So, just Google Philip Kylie
and and you'll find me. I I finally beat
out that guy who is a doctor in Vermont
who has my same name. But the best place
to connect is going to be number one on
Twitter, Philip Kylie there. Number two,
LinkedIn. And you can always just hit me
up, send me a DM, send me an email. I
love talking about AI engineering. I
love talking about inference and I'd be
thrilled to hear what you're working on.
>> Philip, thanks so much for joining me on
the show.
>> Jeff, thanks so much for having me. It's
been a pleasure. This is Jeff Doolittle
for Software Engineering Radio. Thanks
for listening.
[music]
>> Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
[music]
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, [music]
or through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
[music] This and all other episodes of
SE Radio is licensed under Creative
Common License 2.5. Thanks for
listening.